<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: WCAI | Josh Wilson]]></title>
  <link href="http://jwils.me/blog/categories/wcai/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jwils.me/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-17T12:53:18-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jwils.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Josh Wilson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Displaying a S3 Bucket as Nested Directories in Rails]]></title>
    <link href="http://jwils.me/blog/2013/01/02/displaying-s3-bucket-as-nested-directories-in-rails/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-02T17:47:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://jwils.me/blog/2013/01/02/displaying-s3-bucket-as-nested-directories-in-rails</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The component of the app I am currently working on for WCAI, researchers need to be able to download data files. Many of these files are more than a gigabyte in length. After deciding to store the files on S3, it was important to create a secure and easy to use interface to access and download these files.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Here is the files model I created to treat files stored on aws the same as things stored in the database.</p>

<p>``` ruby models/project_file.rb /code/project_file.rb Download
class ProjectFile
  attr_accessor :children, :size, :path</p>

<p>  EXT_MAP =  {</p>

<pre><code>  'xls'  =&gt; :xls,
  'xlsx' =&gt; :xls,
  'doc'  =&gt; :doc,
  'docx' =&gt; :doc,
  'zip'  =&gt; :zip,
  'txt'  =&gt; :txt,
  'pdf'  =&gt; :pdf,
  'sql'  =&gt; :sql,
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  def self.find_by_project_name(name)</p>

<pre><code>project_files = self.files.all({:prefix =&gt; name})
output_files = Hash.new
file_lookup = Hash.new 
root = nil

project_files.each do |project_file|
  file_lookup[project_file.key] = convert(project_file)
end

 file_lookup.values.each do |project_file|
  if project_file.parent_name.nil?
    root = project_file
  else
    parent = file_lookup[project_file.parent_name]
    parent.children ||= []
    parent.children  &lt;&lt; project_file
  end
 end
return root
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def self.find_link_by_name(name)</p>

<pre><code>fog_file = self.files.get(name)
expiration = Time.now + 60.seconds
fog_file.url(expiration)
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def self.convert(fog_file)</p>

<pre><code>file = ProjectFile.new
file.size = fog_file.content_length
file.path = fog_file.key
file.children = nil
return file
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def self.files</p>

<pre><code>FOG_STORAGE.directories.get(Settings.aws_bucket).files
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def extension</p>

<pre><code>ext = self.path[path.rindex(/\./) + 1..-1]
EXT_MAP[ext]
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def extension_css</p>

<pre><code>unless extension.nil?
  extension.to_s
else
  "default"
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def file_name</p>

<pre><code>parent_index = path.rindex(/\//,-2)
if parent_index.nil?
  path
else
  path[parent_index +1..-1]
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def parent_name</p>

<pre><code>parent_index = path.rindex(/\//,-2)
if parent_index.nil?
  nil
else
  path[0..parent_index]
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def is_directory?</p>

<pre><code>not children.nil?
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def str_size</p>

<pre><code>  if size &gt; 1024 * 1024 * 1024
    "%0.0f GB" % (size / (1024 * 1024 * 1024))
  elsif size &gt; 1024 * 1024
    "%0.0f MB" % (size / (1024 * 1024 ))
  else
    "%0.0f KB" % (size / 1024)
  end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>Files are displayed to uses using a tutorial on <a href="http://homework.nwsnet.de/releases/ea21/">collapse tree for file structures</a>. A simple helper function converts the data structure to the proper nested list explained in this example.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Beginning the Project]]></title>
    <link href="http://jwils.me/blog/2012/11/02/beginning-the-project/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-02T15:12:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jwils.me/blog/2012/11/02/beginning-the-project</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Many great web frameworks exist; for this project I chose Ruby on Rails. Since the framework is so popular, gems (extensions) exist that will greatly simplify much of the process. Rails also has a great support community available to help when I run into trouble.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>A few examples of great gems are:
devise cancan, and rolify - Together these gems provide a very powerful and robust way of managing users and permissions. The app has three permission levels researchers, researcher assistants, and admins. Each of these groups will have certain rights and retrictions which are easily managed through these gems.</p>

<p>fog - used to interact with amazon web services through ruby code. Fog can manage amazon instances and files though simple ruby functions.</p>

<p>twitter-bootstrap-rails and simple-form-for - automatically makes forms with bootstrap components, greatly improving design with minimal additional coding.</p>

<h2>Personal Goals</h2>

<p>Setting personal goals outside the simple scope of the project is important to me. I am still learning, and a good way to keep learning is to focus on things that I need to improve while working on a project.</p>

<p>I have a few goals for this project, but most importantly I want to focus on testing. Testing is extremely useful, both for making sure code does what is expected, and ensuring that code wont be broken in the future.</p>

<p>Unfortunately I often overlook testing though. It is often hard to see the time that it saves since it doesn't directly convert to progress on the site. However, it saves a lot of time by catching errors before they are published. It also is often easier to design a function when you can test in as you build.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Storing Analytics Data on AWS]]></title>
    <link href="http://jwils.me/blog/2012/10/30/storing-analytics-data-on-aws/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-30T23:44:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jwils.me/blog/2012/10/30/storing-analytics-data-on-aws</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently The Wharton Customer Analytics Initiative began looking into ways to store research projects online.  I did some research for them to determine the options for using AWS versus in-house solutions. In the end we decided to use EBS backed instances on AWS because of the reasonable price and flexibility that it offers. Here’s a little information on how we arrived at our decision.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Background</h2>

<p><a href="http://www.wharton.upenn.edu/wcai/%20WCAI">WCAI</a> (The Wharton Customer Analytics Initiative) is "The world's preeminent academic research center focusing on the development and application of customer analytics methods." Every few months WCAI receives a dataset from a corporate partner (ranging from ticket sales on StubHub to email marking data from Charming Shoppes). After receiving the data, WCAI does some queries and a basic analysis of the data before sending the data to top researchers across the country. Throughout the research process WCAI supports the researchers by providing access to the data as well as performing any additional queries they may need.</p>

<p>Currently there is no standardized way to store the data for the life of the project. The raw files are submitted and stored on box.com, but for analysis they must be loaded into a database. Some projects are loaded into a MySQL or Postgres database on Wimi-Cruncher (the in-house server), others are stored locally on researchers' computers in a database program like Microsoft Access. Our goal is to create a uniform long-term storage solution for new projects.</p>

<h2>Proposal</h2>

<p>The wimi-crucher server is outdated, so in the process of looking at ways to replaces the server I was asked to estimate the cost of running future projects on Amazon Web Services. Here's a quick table of the per project estimated costs on Amazon.</p>

<table border="1" style="margin-left: .1pt; border-collapse: collapse;">
    <tr>
        <td><strong>Service</strong></td>
        <td><strong>Use</strong></td>
        <td><strong>Price per Unit</strong></td>
        <td><strong>Unit Usage</strong></td>
        <td><strong>Estimated Monthly Cost</strong></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>S3</td>
        <td>Storing raw files</td>
        <td>$0.125 per GB month</td>
        <td>40 GB</td>
        <td>$5</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>EC2 Machine (High-Memory Double Extra Large Instances)</td>
        <td>Perform SQL queries</td>
        <td>$0.9 per Hour</td>
        <td>20 Hours per week</td>
        <td>$72</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>EC2 Storage</td>
        <td>Storing computer hard drive</td>
        <td>$0.10 per GB Month</td>
        <td>40 GB</td>
        <td>$4</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>Data out</td>
        <td>Downloading Data</td>
        <td>$0.125 per GB</td>
        <td>100 GB</td>
        <td>$12.50</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td></td>
        <td></td>
        <td></td>
        <td><strong>TOTAL</strong></td>
        <td><strong>$93.50</strong></td>
    </tr>
</table>


<p>AWS also offers great additional features such as image backup, the ability to change instance sizes as needed, and Glacier, a cheap long-term data storage solution.</p>

<p>Notice that we can also only pay for the server hours we need. Since server usage is charged by the hour, we only have to pay for the hours we have an instance up to perform queries.</p>

<p>Compared to the cost of purchasing a server or buying a virtual machine though Penn, this was by far the cheapest and most flexible choice, so we made the decision to set it up for the next project.</p>

<h2>Implementation</h2>

<p>While AWS has done a fantastic job at providing many simple and intuitive ways to control instances, we want to be able to provide a straightforward method for a researcher to spin up a project instance and perform queries without having to understand too much of the underlying infrastructure. I have been assigned the task of creating an app to perform this functionality, and will describe the implementation choices I made in future posts.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
